{"tossups": [{"question": "These organisms show high clustering coefficients in graphs describing their interactions. In California\u2019s coastal regions, the Pisaster genus acts as one of these organisms. Though not synonymous, ecosystem engineers such as beavers act as these organisms. (*) Cascade effects stem from the absence of these organisms, and a classic example is the apex-predator wolves in Yellowstone National Park. For 10 points, name this type of organism that has a disproportionate impact on its environment, named for an architectural element.", "answer": "keystone species [prompt on specific species or roles like primary producer, apex predator etc. with \u201cwhat is their greater role in the ecological community?\u201d] ", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "C. L. R. James\u2019s At the Rendezvous of Victory takes its name from a work by this author. In a play by this author, the Yoruban trickster Eshu is offended after not being invited to an engagement party. This author set one work in \u201cthis inert town\u2026 at the end of daybreak.\u201d This author of (*) \u201cReturn to my Native Land,\u201d founded the literary journal L'\u00c9tudiant noir. This writer depicted the Black Caliban as the hero of A Tempest. For 10 points, name this Martinique-born author who, along with L\u00e9on Damas and L\u00e9opold Senghor, founded the Negritude movement.", "answer": "Aime Cesaire ", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Six people died in a clash between this organization\u2019s members and the American Legion during an Armistice Day parade in Centralia, Washington. A leader of this organization named Elizabeth Gurley Flynn chained herself to a lamp post to evade arrest during one of this organization\u2019s \u201cfree speech fights\u201d. Joe (*) Hill authored this organization\u2019s \u201cLittle Red Songbook\u201d, which coined the term \u201cpie in the sky\u201d. Bill Haywood and Eugene Debs convened this organization\u2019s first meeting, the \u201cIndustrial Congress\u201d. For 10 points, name this prominent union whose members were known as \u201cwobblies\u201d.", "answer": "Industrial Workers of the World [or IWW, accept Wobblies before mention] ", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "It\u2019s not Marshall McLuhan, but this thinker derived the name of his most famous concept from a passage in Finnegan\u2019s Wake. This thinker utilized Adolf Bastian\u2019s theory of \u201cfolk\u201d and \u201celementary\u201d ideas. A 17-stage process formulated by this thinker describes \u201ccrossing the threshold\u201d after the \u201crefusal of the call\u201d and a (*) \u201ccall to adventure.\u201d This author of The Masks of God described a cycle exemplified by the \u201cjourney\u201d in The Odyssey. For 10 points, name this comparative mythologist who developed the concept of the \u201cmonomyth\u201d in The Hero with a Thousand Faces.", "answer": "Joseph Campbell ", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "This character titles a ballet set in the Four Seasons department store by Johann Strauss II. Fairies named for the season transform grasshoppers and dragonflies into servants in a ballet titled for this character. This character played by Anna Kendrick helps the Baker raise Little Red and Jack in the film adaptation of Into the Woods. (*) Don Magnifico replaces this character\u2019s evil stepmother in Rossini\u2019s La Cenerentola. For ten points, name this character who loses her glass slipper in a Sergei Prokofiev ballet.", "answer": "Cinderella [or Angelina or Zolushka or Aschenbr\u00f6del or Grete or Aschenputtel, prompt on La Cenerentola before mentioned] ", "subcategory": "Other Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A Fresnel rhomb is a device that uses this phenomenon twice to induce a phase shift in polarized light. A microscopy technique that uses this phenomenon induces fluorescence by means of evanescent waves which are attenuated when this phenomenon (*) frustrated. Snell\u2019s window occurs underwater as a result of this phenomenon which exists because refraction cannot bend light more than 90 degrees. Light past the critical angle bounces rather than refracts in, for 10 points, this phenomenon seen in water glasses and swimming pools.", "answer": "total internal reflection [or TIR; do NOT accept or prompt on \u201creflection\u201d] ", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This city contains its state's only memorial of a Confederate sailor at its Louis Amateis-designed Dignified Resignation monument. Geoffrey Jellicoe\u2019s last landscaping project in the United States was this city\u2019s Moody Gardens. After the deadliest natural disaster in American history took place in this city, a 10-mile long (*) seawall was built to minimize future damage. For 10 points, name this Texas city devastated by a Category 4 Hurricane in 1900.", "answer": "Galveston ", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s ruler Azemilcus was spared from crucifixion after a siege of this city. Bishop Paulinus constructed a church atop this city\u2019s ancient temple to Melqart. Rocks created from the destruction of part of this city were used to build a (*) causeway that resulted in it permanently becoming a peninsula. That causeway was built by Alexander the Great. A product named for this city was created when Murex snails were left in lead vats to decompose. For 10 points, name this Phoenecian port city that names a type of purple dye. ", "answer": "Tyre ", "subcategory": "Ancient History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This figure created a tyrannical regime with 59,999 citizens on the island of Pelan. While growing up in Mecca, this figure was given the nickname \u201cbig head.\u201d This man attempted to isolate a \u201cbrown germ\u201d from a \u201cblack germ\u201d through killing (*) dark-skinned babies. 600 years after this man\u2019s death at the age of 152, his followers completed the creation of a \u201cdevil\u201d race. For 10 points, name this creator of white people in Nation of Islam theology.", "answer": "Doctor Yakub ", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "Rudolph Steiner\u2019s sculpture The Representative of Humanity accompanied a lecture titled for Christ, Lucifer, and this mythical figure. To prevent rain and dry the earth, this god created the three-headed dragon Azi Dahaka. The hermaphroditic teenager Gayomart died 30 years after receiving wounds inflicted by this son of (*) Zurvan. For 10 points, name this personification of evil in Zoroastrianism who opposes Ahura Mazda.", "answer": "Ahriman [or Angra Mainyu] ", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "An anecdote about this ruler relates how he measured the shortest distance between two railway stations by drawing a straight line between them with a ruler. This ruler's \"Third Section\" secret police was headed by his minister Alexander Benckendorff. Frederic Chopin's Revolutionary Etudes were inspired by an uprising against this ruler known as the (*) Cadet Revolution. Pavel Pestel protested the \"illegal succession\" of this ruler after the death of his predecessor Alexander I. For 10 points, what Russian tsar was targeted by the Decembrist revolt?", "answer": "Tsar Nicholas I Pavlovich Romanov (accept Nikolai in place of \"Nicholas\" do NOT accept or prompt on \"Nicholas II\") ", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Lady Meux is depicted in a white dress in one work in this series. The tall masts of ships rise in the background of one work in this series set in Valparaiso Bay. A work in this series depicts a man on the edge of a boat traveling under the title structure and is subtitled (*) Old Battersea Bridge. A work in this series was inspired by a light show in the Cremorne Gardens and is subtitled the Falling Rocket. For 10 points, name this painting series by James Whistler that includes a painting in Black and Gold and is usually set at night. ", "answer": "James Abbott McNeill Whistler\u2019s nocturnes [accept Nocturne in Black and Gold - the Falling Rocket, accept Nocturne in Pink and Grey - Portrait of Lady Meux, accept Nocturne in Blue and Gold - Old Battersea Bridge, - accept Nocturne in Blue and Gold - Valparaiso Bay] ", "subcategory": "Painting", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In a song titled for this figure, Young Thug says to \u201cgo apeshit, go Godzilla, bae, back it up\u201d while an Elon Musk song says this figure is \u201csippin on some Bombay\u201d. A Remington 870 shotgun ended this figure\u2019s life just one day after his 17th birthday. A Vine of Danny Trejo spawned a meme telling others to flash their (*) genitals for this figure, and false reports showed this figure receiving 11,000 posthumous votes in the 2016 presidential election. For 10 points, name this figure, a western lowland gorilla who was killed at the Cincinnati Zoo in 2016.", "answer": "Harambe ", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "An algebraic field is a ring with a property named for this mathematician over both addition and multiplication. This mathematician is the alphabetically first namesake of a theorem proved by showing there is no solvable Galois group over a certain splitting field. This mathematician proved that it was impossible to find a general formula for the (*) roots of a polynomial above degree 5 in a theorem he names with Paolo Ruffini. For ten points, name this Norwegian mathematician who names groups whose operation is commutative.", "answer": "Niels Henrik Abel ", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In a novel by this author, a pipe welded to a steel sphere on a railcar is offered as an explanation why \u201cthe moment was structured that way\u201d. In another novel by this author, two people who must die within a week of each other are a duprass while a wampeter is the hub around which a karass is structured. The doctrine of foma, or (*) \u201charmless untruths\u201d, is the religion of San Lorenzo in that novel by this author. For 10 points, name this author who described Bokononism and Tralfamadorian thought in his novels Cat\u2019s Cradle and Slaughterhouse Five.", "answer": "Kurt Vonnegut ", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "NOTE TO PLAYERS: two answers required. After one character\u2019s boat capsizes, he agrees to accept another character\u2019s offer of these two things under the condition that he is left alone. In a book written with only 50 words, a yellow furred character offers the main character these two items \u201cin a box\u201d and \u201cwith a (*) fox\u201d and \u201cin a house'' and \u201cwith a mouse.\u201d One character in a work titled for these two items claims \u201cI do not like them here or there / I do not like them anywhere!\u201d Sam-I-Am offers the unnamed main character, for 10 points, what two strangely-colored title foods of a Dr. Seuss book.", "answer": "green eggs and ham [accept equivalents, prompt on partial answer] ", "subcategory": "Other Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This leader initiated the Mengo Crisis when he ordered an invasion of Mutesa II\u2019s palace. This leader\u2019s second rise to power ended in a conflict sometimes called the Luwero War. This leader seized 60% of private property in a policy known as the \u201cMove to the Left\u201d. This leader described his socialist policies in his (*) \u201cCommon Man\u2019s Charter\u201d. While on a state visit to Singapore, this leader was overthrown by an uncrowned king of Scotland in a coup d\u2019etat. For 10 points, name this Ugandan president that both preceded and succeeded Idi Amin.", "answer": "Apolo Milton Obote ", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This musician\u2019s performance of another composer\u2019s piano concerto in A minor inspired Edvard Grieg to write a piano concerto in the same key. This musician performed their Three Romances for Piano and Violin with its dedicatee, Joseph Joachim. It\u2019s not Liszt, but this musician popularized performing from memory. This musician may have had an affair with Johannes (*) Brahms after her husband was sent to an asylum. For ten points, name this pianist who married the composer of the Rhenish Symphony.", "answer": "Clara Schumann [or Clara Wieck, prompt on Schumann] ", "subcategory": "Music", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In a play by this author, Chispa, the lover of Rebolledo, crossdresses as a soldier and sings a marching song. At the end of another play by this author, Astolfo marries Rosaura to preserve her honor. In a play by this author, Don Alvaro is garotted in jail, after which Pedro Crespo is appointed to the title position. This author wrote a play in which (*) Basilio, King of Poland, imprisons his son, Segismundo because he fears he will become a tyrant. For 10 points, name this Spanish Golden Age playwright of The Mayor of Zalamea and Life is a Dream.", "answer": "Pedro Calderon de la Barca ", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Description Acceptable: The strongest theoretical super acid is one of these compounds. Another of these compounds was the first Rydberg compound discovered as well as the largest diatomic molecule. Ultraviolet excimer lasers use one type of these compounds for their gain media. A (*) clathrate compound of solid hydrogen often qualifies as one of these compounds. Neil Bartlett discovered the first of these compounds produced by a reaction of platinum hexafluoride. For 10 points each, name these compounds that include elements from group 18 like xenon tetrafluoride.", "answer": "noble gas compounds [accept anything describing noble gases forming compounds/molecules] ", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}]}